Guide to the Thomas Welton Stanford Library Time Capsule Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Thomas Welton Stanford Library time capsule collection
1886-1898
SC0646
Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.
2 Linear feet
Collection consists of the items placed in the time capsule by Jane L. Stanford and interred at the cornerstone laying of the library on November 2, 1898. Included are university circulars and registers, entrance exams, commencement programs, photograph of T. W. Stanford, letter by Jane L. Stanford, Bible, crucifix, newspapers of the day, and coins.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Historical Note
Thomas Welton Stanford, Leland Stanford's younger brother, reassigned half of his bequest from Leland Stanford's will to Jane Stanford, who used the funds to build a new library. It was one of the first buildings to be completed in the construction of the outer Quadrangle.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists of the items placed in the time capsule by Jane L. Stanford and interred at the cornerstone laying of the library on November 2, 1898. Included are university circulars and registers, entrance exams, commencement programs, photograph of T. W. Stanford, letter by Jane L. Stanford, Bible, crucifix, newspapers of the day, and coins.
Access Terms
Stanford University -- General subdivision--History.;; Stanford University. Libraries.; Stanford, Thomas Welton, 1832-1918.
Collection Contents
- Time Capsule items
  The original copper box that held these items is cataloged under the number AM-2002-27.
  - Circulars 1-4 Circulars 1 and 2 (1891): Act of the Legislature, Grant of Endowment, Address of Leland Stanford, First Meeting of the Trustees, Laying of the Comer-Stone (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular 3 (1891): Statement of entrance requirements and of other matters preliminary to the organization of the work of instruction for the first year of the university (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular 4 (1891): Announcement of the faculty of the university and an outline of the courses of instruction offered for the academic year 1891-92 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular 5 (1891): Exercises of the Opening Day, Oct 1 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Circular 6 (1891): [directory of faculty and students, admission and graduation requirements, and list of courses] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commencement programs, 1892-1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Entrance exams, 1892-1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exercises of the Opening Day (program), Oct. 1, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Founding Grant publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hymn sung at the cornerstone laying of the TWS Library [manuscript, probably in Bertha Berner's hand], Nov. 2, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Thomas Welton Stanford, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Schedule of lectures and recitations and directory, 1898-99 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanford Sequoia, Oct. 28, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stanford, Jane Lathrop. Address to Trustees, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Stanford, Jane Lathrop. Letter written to be included in the time capsule, [signed by JLS but letter is probably in Bertha Berner's hand], Nov. 1, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Leland Stanford Junior University Registers, 1891-1897 (Box 1)
  - The Holy Bible. New York: American Bible Society. With inscription by Jane L. Stanford, 1886-1898 (Box 1)
  - Kempis, Thomas A. The Following of Christ; in Four Books. Philadelphia: H. L. Kilner and Co. Crucifix, Crucifix (Box 1)
  - San Francisco Chronicle, Nov. 2, 1898 (Box 2)
  - San Francisco Call, Nov. 2, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Palo Alto Times, Nov. 1, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Palo Alto Live Oak, Oct. 28, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Gold and silver coins (Box 3)
    Patrons must have permission of the University Archivist to view these.